OLCA ORAKCI

linkedin.com/in/olcaorakci | gerult.github.io

Data Scientist | Machine Learning Engineer | Full-stack Developer +90 5449622217 | olcaorakci@gmail.com

SUMMARY

A data scientist and software engineer with 5 years of experience in deploying successful machine learning and AI solutions across diverse industries such as telecommunication, finance, automotive, and physics. Realized 18 data-driven industry projects and 4 academic projects, all completed successfully.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, SQL, JavaScript, HTML **AI:** PyTorch, TensorFlow, scikit-learn, XGBoost, LightGBM

Analysis: Pandas, PySpark, NumPy, SciPy **Visualization:** Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly **Tools:** Git, Docker, Rest, Kafka, OpenCV

Domain: NLP, LLMs, Reinforcement Learning, Computer Vision, Forecasting, Anomaly Detection

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Data Scientist, Innova IT Solutions

Dec 2021 - Present

- Achieved annual cost savings of approximately €2M through a predictive battery cycle life model that ensured efficient allocation of battery investments.
- Facilitated a 63% reduction in field operator fault detection time through the development of a faulty cable detection system utilizing deep learning technologies.
- Led a team of five in developing a state-of-the-art computer vision solution to detect router malfunctions with 93.6% precision.

Machine Learning Engineer, Mobirob

May 2021 - Dec 2021

- Produced the back-end of machine learning powered software for a cost-effective laser vision sensor for a high-precision (0.01mm) industrial measurement operation.
- Developed an OCR in the wild application using 3D sensor data in the automotive sector. material, reducing human error risks by 16%.

Volunteer Data Scientist, Astronomical Optical Laboratory

Aug 2019 - Feb 2021

- Enhanced ground telescope imaging by a +0.134 Strehl ratio through the Deep Deterministic Policy Gradient algorithm, presented findings at EuroCC Winter School 2021
- Delivered applied machine learning workshop for 50+ people at Deep Learning and Artificial Intelligence in Astronomy Workshop, Ege University, Turkey (2020)
- Classified objects with 96.7% accuracy in Sloan Digital Sky Survey data utilizing XGBoost, showcased at 1st Workshop on High-Performance Computing & Applications, Middle East Technical University (2019)

Volunteer Data Scientist, Prophoton

Aug 2019 - Jun 2020

• Attained 99.5% spatial accuracy with Convolutional Neural Networks for spectral splitting and light concentration., presented at Fotonik 2019, Koç University

FREELANCE EXPERIENCE

LLM Powered Web Application: Created a web application to automatically fill documents using LLMs

2023

AI Trainer: Directed the AI training sessions at an Erasmus+ Project LTTA event in the Czech Republic.

2023

REWARDS

IDC Turkey Summit Best Future of Intelligence Award for 2023

TM Forum's Excellence in Network Agility Award for 2023, Finalist

EDUCATION

Middle East Technical University MSc, Multimedia Informatics

Mar 2021 - Present

Middle East Technical University BSc, Physics

Sep 2014 - Jan 2021